招待に応じてこの大会を
視聴してくださっている皆さんを
We extend a warm welcome
to all who accepted an invitation
to join us for this convention.
温かく歓迎いたします
今の世の中で本当の友達を
見つけるのは簡単ではありません
We live in an unfriendly world
where true friends are hard to find.
Is it possible to draw close to God
and have him as our Friend?
では 神と親しくなって友達に
なることはできるのでしょうか
If so, what must we do
to gain God’s friendship?
もしできるとしたら
何をすればよいのでしょうか
Brother Kenneth Cook,
a member of the Governing Body,
統治体の成員 ケニス･クック兄弟が
講演の中でそうした点に
答えてくださいます
will answer those questions
in the discourse entitled
“Friendship With God—How Possible?”
主題は 「神と友達になるには」です
神と友達になることなんて
できないと思いますか
Is it realistic to believe
that you can be a friend of God?
If until now you’ve answered no
to that question,
そう思っている皆さんに
ぜひ知っていただきたい点があります
please consider this:
The lives of millions of people today
今 何百万人もの人たちは
prove that friendship with God is possible.
実際に神と友達になっています
Their lives prove that we can find
a peaceful and meaningful life now,
その人たちは平和で充実した毎日を送り
as well as hope
for an everlasting and peaceful future.
いつまでも平和に暮らせる
という希望を持っています
If you desire that for yourself and others,
自分もそうなりたいと思うなら
ぜひ聖書に基づくこの話を
聞いてください
we urge you
to listen to this Scriptural talk.
なぜ聞いていただきたいかというと
We emphasize the need to listen
because many people ignore
that important question,
多くの人は神の友達になれるのか
という重要な質問について
that is, Can you be a friend of God?
考えようとしないからです
Why is it that many put
such an important question out of their mind?
多くの人がこのことを
気に留めないのはなぜでしょうか
There are a number of reasons.
理由はさまざまです
For example, some believe
that God is impersonal or unknowable
ある人たちは 神なんて
遠い存在だと考えています
神はいないとか 人間には
関心がないと言う人もいます
or that he does not exist
and that he’s not interested in humans.
They are taught that God is a mystery
神は謎めいていて 残酷で 厳しくて
and that he’s cruel, harsh, and demanding.
要求ばかりすると言う人もいます
Many religious leaders claim
that God will punish bad people forever
多くの宗教では 神が悪人を永遠の
責め苦に遭わせると教えています
in a place of torment.
Do you feel drawn into friendship
with a God like that?
そのような神と友達に
なりたいと思いますか
Who in their right mind would?
とてもそうは思えないでしょう
Still other people, after seeing
ある人たちは 世の中の
不公正や苦しみを見て
all of the injustice and suffering
in the world,
神は死んでしまったに違いないとか
have concluded that God must be dead
初めからいなかったんだと言います
or that he never existed at all.
And then there are those who believe
ある人たちは 自分は悪いことを
たくさんしてしまったので
that they have done
too many bad things in their life
神の友達になんてなれないと
思っています
to ever be a friend of God.
Do any of those causes for doubt or concern
apply to you?
あなたもそんなふうに
思ったことがありますか
もしそうなら この話は
きっと役立つでしょう
If so, please listen carefully
to the following four key points
4つの点を考えます
that may help you to see
that friendship with God is truly possible.
自分も神と友達になれると
思えるかもしれません
では考えていきましょう
We will then develop each one.
1つ目に 私たちを神から
引き離したのは罪です
First, we’ll look at how sin
separates us from God.
Second, we’ll look at how God
has taken the initiative to heal the breach
2つ目に 神は人間のために
自分の方から行動し
and bring obedient humans
back into friendship with him.
良い関係を取り戻せるように
してくださいました
Then, we’ll examine what we can do
3つ目に いつまでも
神の友達でいるためには
to become God’s friend in an everlasting way.
しなければならないことがあります
And finally, we will consider
how friendship with God
4つ目に 神の友達になる人は
今も将来も平和を楽しめます
brings peace now and in the future.
では1つ目の点を考えましょう
So for our first point:
私たちを神から引き離したのは
何でしょうか
What is it that separates us from God?
In a word, sin.
一言で言うと罪です
Why does sin separate us?
なぜそう言えますか
なぜなら 真の神は清く聖なる方で
Because the true God is holy, he’s pure,
and his conduct is perfect.
行いが完全だからです
He does not have a trace of sin;
he’s clean in the highest sense.
罪が全くなく 最高度に清い方です
人間は誰一人 神と同じほど
聖なる状態になることはできません
No human can be holy to that degree,
not even close.
To illustrate: Consider the words
“human” and “imperfect.”
「人間」と「不完全」という言葉に
ついて考えましょう
人間といえば不完全
不完全といえば人間です
They go together, don’t they?
You cannot fully describe humans
without mentioning imperfection.
そうではないでしょうか
It’s just a part of us,
人間の歴史を見ると
and human history shows this
to be sadly and painfully true.
その現実が痛いほどよく分かります
So then our sins or imperfections
罪や不完全さによって壁ができました
create a barrier between us and God.
私たちと神との間にです
This separation is described
私たちは神から
引き離されてしまったのです
at Isaiah 59:2,
その点はイザヤ 59:2に
書かれています
where we are told in part:
「あなたたちは自らの過ちによって
神から引き離された⋯⋯
“Your own errors have separated you
from your God.
Your sins have made him
hide his face from you.”
あなたたちの罪のせいで
神は顔を隠した」
‘Separated from God,’ it says.
「神から引き離された」とあります
We were born into this state,
生まれつきこういう状態です
でも私たちが罪人なのは
but God did not create us to be sinful.
Our sins are not his fault.
人間を造った神のせいではありません
The first humans, Adam and Eve,
were created perfect.
最初の人アダムとエバは完全でした
But they proved to be ungrateful and selfish,
でも神への感謝を忘れて自分勝手になり
神との友情を失いました
and they rejected God’s friendship.
They destroyed their peace with God
by sinning against him,
神に罪を犯したので 神と
平和な関係でいられなくなり
and they became his enemies.
敵になりました
Adam then passed sin on
2人から生まれた子孫は
罪と死を受け継ぎました
to his descendants, as well as death.
We read about this terrible inheritance
どれほどひどい結果になったかが
at Romans 5:12.
ローマ 5:12に書かれています
In this verse, the apostle Paul summarizes
ここで使徒パウロは
罪と死がどう関係しているのかを
why our inherited sinful condition
leads to death.
短い言葉で説明しています
こうあります
He wrote:
“That is why, just as through one man
「このような訳で 1人の人によって
人類に罪が入り
“sin entered into the world
and death through sin,
罪によって死が入り
“and so death spread to all men
こうして全ての人が罪人になったために
because they had all sinned.”
死が全ての人に広がった」
“Death spread to all men.”
「死が全ての人に広が」りました
この罪というパンデミックは
This pandemic of sin
has a 100 percent infection rate
感染率が100パーセントです
and a 100 percent mortality rate.
死亡率も100パーセントです
誰も逃れられません
No human can escape it.
「全ての人が罪人になったために
As Paul said: “Death spread . . .
because they had all sinned.”
死が⋯⋯広がった」とあります
On our own,
we cannot correct our sinful state.
自力ではこの状態から
抜け出すことができません
It’s as if we have fallen into a deep pit
深い穴の中に落ちて
出口が見えないようなものです
with seemingly no way out.
But are we left without hope?
でも希望がないわけではありません
No.
神は全ての人を敵と見ている
わけではないのです
In fact, although God views some people
as his enemies,
he treats others as his friends.
ご自分の友と見ている人もいます
For example, regarding the man Abraham,
例えば 「ヤコブの手紙」 2:23は
the Bible book of James
says in chapter 2 and verse 23
アブラハムという人について
こう言っています
that “Abraham put faith in Jehovah,
「『アブラハムはエホバに信仰を持ち
“and it was counted to him as righteousness,
そのことは正しいと見なされた』⋯⋯
and he came to be called Jehovah’s friend.”
アブラハムはエホバの友と
呼ばれるようになったのです」
Abraham was as imperfect as we are,
アブラハムは私たちと同様
不完全でした
でも 神の友と呼ばれる
ようになりました
but he came to be called God’s friend.
What has God done
to make it possible for humans
不完全な人間がどうして神の友達に
なることができるのでしょうか
to gain his favor and blessing?
簡単に言うと 神の方から
行動してくださいました
Simply put, our Creator
has taken the initiative.
He has taken steps to heal the breach
that was caused by sin
私たちとの良い関係を
取り戻すために行動し
and to eliminate the separation
between us and him.
私たちが神に近づけるように
してくださったのです
どのようにでしょうか
How has he done this?
First, the Holy Scriptures tell us
まず聖書によると
神は私たちがご自分を知り
that God desires for us to come to know him
and to be at peace with him.
ご自分との友情を育むことを
望んでいます
In fact, he appeals to us to do this.
実際 そうするよう勧めています
使徒 17:27によると
In the Bible book of Acts 17:27,
神は私たちが神を誠実に
知ろうとすることを願っています
we are told that God wants us
to sincerely seek him
and that if we do,
実際「神は 私たち一人一人から
遠く離れてはいません」
we will find that “he is not far off
from each one of us.”
次はとても大切です
Next, and very important,
God took the initiative to make this possible
神は自分の方から
by providing the sacrifice of his Son, Jesus,
子であるイエスを犠牲として
与えてくれました
私たちを罪から自由にするためです
in order to redeem us from sin.
That was an unparalleled act of love.
神はこのようにして
最大の愛を示してくださいました
As we now read 1 John 4:10,
ヨハネ第一 4:10を読みながら
please think about what it says
神がどれほど大きな愛を示してくれたか
について考えてみてください
regarding this matchless act of love
on God’s part
私たちとの間にできた壁を取り除くため
so that we may never forget
that God took the initiative
自分の方から行動してくれたのです
to heal the breach, so to speak.
ヨハネ第一 4:10
First John 4:10 says:
“The love is in this respect,
「私たちが神を愛したというより
“not that we have loved God,
神が私たちを愛し
“but that he loved us
私たちの罪を償う犠牲として
ご自分の子を遣わしてくださったのです
“and sent his Son as a propitiatory sacrifice
これこそが愛です」
for our sins.”
What did God do?
「神［は］私たちを愛し⋯⋯
“God . . . loved us,” it says,
ご自分の子を遣わしてくださ」いました
“and [he] sent his Son.”
This sacrifice that God provided
by means of his Son
神は犠牲としてご自分の子を
遣わしました
is called “propitiatory”
because it can atone for our sins.
その犠牲には罪を「償う」力があります
And here is how it can do so:
どういうことでしょうか
What Jesus gave in sacrifice for us
アダムは完全な命を失いました
was equal to what Adam lost for us,
イエスが犠牲として差し出したのも
that is, a perfect human life.
人間としての完全な命です
Adam exchanged his perfect life for death
アダムは神に反逆してしまったため
by his rebellion against God.
完全な命を失いました
As mentioned earlier, Adam then
passed sin on to his descendants,
その結果 アダムの子孫は
罪を代々受け継ぎ
and he placed us on a path
outside of God’s friendship.
神から引き離され
神との友情を失ったのです
On the other hand,
the death of Jesus allowed for a ransom,
贖いと呼ばれるイエスの犠牲には
アダムが失ったものを
取り戻す力があります
or a means to satisfy God’s justice
so that we could receive back
what Adam lost for us.
神の公正という基準に
かなっているからです
That undeserved gift from God
was given at great cost.
神は大きな犠牲を払って
この贈り物をしてくれました
神は私たちにご自分のことを
知ってほしい
Clearly, our Creator wants us
to come to know him
友達になってほしいと願っているのです
and to enjoy a beautiful friendship with him.
We should be very grateful
that God took the necessary step
私たちが神と親しくなり
友達になれるよう
to close the gap
and provide a way for us
神の方から行動して
道を開いてくれたことを
うれしく思いませんか
to become his friend.
The next step involves each of us.
3つ目です
私たちには何が求められますか
What is required of us?
謙遜さです 神からの贈り物を
謙遜に受け取る必要があります
Humility.
We must be humble enough
to accept God’s gift.
If we are humble, we’ll see
our need for God’s mercy,
謙遜であれば 神の憐れみが
必要であることを認め
and we’ll then do our part
to show appreciation.
感謝を表すために
精いっぱいのことを行うはずです
The Bible book of Acts 3:19 tells us
「使徒の活動」 3:19にある通り
that this involves
‘repenting and turning around.’
「悔い改めて生き方を
変え」なければなりません
In other words, to receive God’s gift,
which includes his mercy,
ですから 憐れみを含む
神からの贈り物を頂くには
we must adjust our thinking by repenting
悔い改めることによって考え方を変え
and then turn around
by adjusting our conduct and course in life
行いや生き方の点で
必要な変化を遂げなければ
ならないのです
wherever necessary.
そうする機会は
全ての人に開かれています
The opportunity to do this
is open to all people.
創造者である神は
全ての人に憐れみを示しています
As our Creator,
God is not partial in his mercy
友達になりたいと思っています
and in the friendship he offers.
そのために必要なことを
全部してくれました
He has kindly put everything in place for us.
私たちがすべきなのは
感謝して 謙遜になり
All we must do is be grateful and humble
and then take the next step.
次のことを行うことです
That step involves accepting Jesus
and his teachings.
イエスとイエスの教えを
受け入れることです
神はイエスの手本に倣うようにと
言っています
God requires that we follow
the example of his Son.
どの程度倣うべきでしょうか
How closely must we do so?
At John 14:6, Jesus explained:
ヨハネ 14:6でイエスは
こう言っています
「私は道であり 真理であり 命です
“I am the way and the truth and the life.
私を通してでなければ 誰も
父のもとに行くことはできません」
No one comes to the Father
except through me.”
“No one.”
ですから 神の友達になるには
So, then, to come into God’s friendship,
we must follow his Son as true Christians.
イエスにしっかり従う必要があります
ここまでで 人間が罪によって
神から引き離されたこと
So far, we have reviewed
how sin separated humans from God.
Then we considered what God has done
to heal the breach, or close the gap,
また私たちが神の友達になれるよう
神がどのように壁を取り除いて
くださったかを考えました
so that we can come back
into his favor as his friends.
Now let’s look even further
into what we must do,
では次の点を考えましょう
私たちは神の友達になるために
which brings us to the third key point:
How can a person become God’s friend?
何をしなければならないでしょうか
We invite you to consider what is said
ご一緒にヤコブ 4:8を開いて
考えてみましょう
at James 4:8.
If you have a copy of the Bible,
we urge you to follow along
聖書をお持ちであれば
どうぞ目で追ってください
ヤコブ 4:8です
—James 4:8.
次の点に注目してください
As we read it,
please notice first the invitation,
どんなことが呼び掛けられているか
then the response,
神は何をしてくれるか
私たちは何をすべきか です
こうあります
and finally what we must do.
It reads:
「神に近づいてください そうすれば
神は近づいてくださいます
“Draw close to God,
and he will draw close to you.
“Cleanse your hands, you sinners,
罪人たち 手を清めてください
and purify your hearts, you indecisive ones.”
優柔不断な人たち
心を清めてください」
まず「神に近づいてください」と
呼び掛けられています
So, first, what is the invitation?
It is to “draw close to God.”
神に近づくなら
神は何をしてくれるでしょうか
That is followed
by what response on God’s part?
“He will draw close to you.”
「近づいてくださいます」
But for God to do this, what must we do
でも神に近づいてもらうため
しなければならないことがあります
to show that we accept his invitation?
We must cleanse and purify ourselves
according to his standards.
神の基準に従って
自分を清めなければなりません
そのためには努力が必要です
This will take effort.
神の基準を学ばなければなりません
For example,
we must learn about his standards,
and we must come to appreciate
that they are the best for us,
その基準が一番
良いものであることを信じ
それに従うことを決意
しなければなりません
and then we must be determined
to follow them.
Above all, we do this
because we want to please God
神に喜ばれたい 神の友達になりたい
という気持ちからそうします
and to be his friend.
では どうすれば神との友情を
育てられるでしょうか
So, then, how can you develop
a friendship with God?
Show initiative and put forth the effort.
進んで行動し努力することです
Consider this: If you have a houseplant,
植物を育てているとしましょう
you know that it doesn’t grow on its own.
植物には世話が必要です
You have to water it regularly
定期的に水をやり 成長に適した環境を
整えなければなりません
and keep it in an environment
that helps it to grow.
True?
神との友情を育てるためにも
同じようなことが必要です
Something similar is true
of our friendship with God.
We nurture this friendship by reading
and studying God’s Word, the Bible.
聖書を学ぶことによって
神との友情を育てることができます
When we do so,
we learn important things about God.
聖書から神について
大切なことを学べます
For example,
we learn that God’s name is Jehovah.
神の名がエホバであることが分かります
私たちは友達を名前で呼びます
And as is true of any good friendship,
it’s important that we use his name.
ですから 神の名を使うことは大切です
If we’re sincere in our efforts
to “draw close” to him,
ヤコブ 4:8に書かれている通り
私たちが神に「近づ」くために
誠実に努力するなら
as we read at James 4:8,
Jehovah will “draw close” to us.
エホバは「近づ」いてくださいます
エホバは 決して
真の友を見捨てたりしません
And he never abandons his true friends.
In fact, John 17:3 tells us
that coming to know God
ヨハネ 17:3にある通り
神のことを知るなら
“means everlasting life” for us.
「永遠の命を得る」ことができます
What an undeserved kindness
and priceless gift
これはエホバが真の友に
惜しみなく与える
for Jehovah’s true friends!
貴重な贈り物です
あなたも神の友達になって
幸せに暮らしたいと思いませんか
So that you too can enjoy
a bright future as God’s friends,
we warmly invite you to accept
a free interactive Bible course
そうであれば ぜひエホバの証人と
無料の聖書レッスンを楽しんでください
offered by Jehovah’s Witnesses
テキストは「いつまでも幸せに
暮らせます」という出版物です
using the publication Enjoy life Forever!
Here’s what it looks like.
これです
Jehovah’s Witnesses can help you
to get either a printed
エホバの証人から印刷版や電子版を
入手することができます
or an electronic copy.
最初の3つのレッスンは
「聖書はどのように役立つ？」
It begins with the lessons:
“How Can the Bible Help You?”
「聖書を読むと希望が持てる」
“The Bible Gives Hope,”
「聖書は信用できる本？」です
and “Can You Trust the Bible?”
We urge you to learn these things
こうした点を学び
and to worship God in harmony with the truth
書かれている真理に沿って
神を崇拝するようお勧めします
that is revealed in his Word.
So, what important points have we considered
ここまでで 神の友達になるには
どうしたらよいかについて考えました
regarding how a person
can become God’s friend?
まず聖書を学んで
神について知ることです
First, get to know God
by reading and studying his Word.
イエスは そうすれば
「永遠の命を得」られると言いました
Jesus said that doing this
“means everlasting life.”
And then,
そして神の名を知り 使うことです
learn about God’s name and use it.
神の友達になりたいと願う人が
しなければならないことは
Now we’ll list four more things
that those who desire
to become God’s friends must do.
ほかにもあります
They are: imitate God’s qualities,
神の性格に倣うこと
神が嫌うことを考えたり
行ったりしないこと
reject thinking and actions that offend God,
associate with those
who want to be God’s friend,
神の友達になりたい人と交友を持つこと
and avoid friendship with people
神の基準を無視したり
ばかにしたりする人と
who ignore or mock God’s standards.
付き合わないようにすることです
Now, a few things in that list
speak for themselves—don’t they?—
今挙げた中に 神の友達に
なりたい人との交友を持ち
such as associate with those
who want to be God’s friend
神の基準を無視したり
ばかにしたりする人と
and avoid friendship with people
who ignore or mock God’s standards.
付き合わないように
することがありました
これは当然ではないでしょうか
That makes sense, doesn’t it?
先ほどの植物の例えを
思い出してください
Think back to our illustration
about the houseplant.
水や肥料をやるだけでなく
You must not only water and nurture it,
but you must keep it
in the right environment,
植物が成長しやすい環境を
整えなければなりません
one that helps it to grow.
Likewise, associating with those
who also want to be God’s friend
私たちにも良い環境が必要です
そのためには 神の友になりたい人を
友にしなければなりません
is the right environment for us.
では 神の性格に倣うことについては
どうでしょうか
But what about the requirement
to imitate God’s qualities?
How can imperfect people do this?
不完全な私たちにできるのでしょうか
Well, for a few minutes,
we’ll look at just two of God’s qualities
神の性格の2つの特徴を取り上げ
どのように倣えるかを考えましょう
and how we can imitate him.
And we will begin with God’s love.
まず愛について考えます
An important way that we can imitate
God’s love and become his friend
神のような愛を身に着け
神の友達になるには
is by applying what his Son, Jesus,
taught us.
イエスが教えたことを
実践しなければなりません
For example, Jesus said:
例えばイエスはこう教えました
“Just as you want men to do to you,
「人からしてほしいと思う通りに
人にもしなさい」
do the same way to them”
シンプルな教えですが
実践するには努力が要ります
—a simple statement
but one that takes effort to apply, true?
Can we do this?
でも不可能なことではありません
Yes.
And a person who desires to be God’s friend
神の友達になりたいと思う人は
will put forth the effort needed to do this.
そのために一生懸命努力します
To succeed in imitating God’s love,
神の愛に倣うには 神のような愛情深い
まなざしで人々を見る必要があります
we must try to see people
as Jehovah sees them.
相手の身になって考え
何を必要とし 何を心配し
We must try to put ourselves
in the place of others
so that we can understand
their needs, their concerns,
どんな心の痛みを抱えているかを
理解するよう努めましょう
and even their pain of heart.
けがや病気や老化のために
Some may be challenged physically
because of injury, disease, or aging.
つらい思いをしているかもしれません
Others are coping with emotional trials
気分が落ち込んだり 心配事を
抱えたりしている人もいることでしょう
because of depression or anxiety.
Many people face difficulties
that we have not experienced.
その人にしか分からないような
問題もあります
例えば 若い人には高齢の人の気持ちが
なかなか分からないかもしれません
For instance, a young person
may find it hard
to understand older people,
and he or she will really need to think
about what it must be like
ちょっと考えただけでは
年を取るというのが
どういうことか分からないでしょう
to be an older person.
If that is true of you,
how can you imitate God’s love?
では どうすれば神のような愛を
身に着けられるでしょうか
高齢の人の気持ちがある程度
理解できるようになるまで
One important way is by listening carefully
until you understand
the other person’s feelings.
話によく耳を傾けることです
When you do so, you are in a better position
そうすれば 神のような愛を
少しずつ身に着けられます
to imitate God’s love.
エホバの友達になりたいと
思っている人は
Those who desire to be Jehovah’s friends
will be moved to imitate his love
エホバの愛に倣い 相手が本当に
必要としている事柄を考えて行動します
by acting according
to what others really need.
That brings us to a second
and related quality,
では 神の性格の2つ目の特徴である
親切に注目しましょう
that of kindness.
神の友達になりたいと思う人は
Anyone who desires to be God’s friend
must be kind to others.
人に親切でなければなりません
Here again, we can learn much
from what Jesus said and did.
この点についてもイエスの
言動から多くを学べます
イエスは至高者である神が
God’s Son said that the Most High
“is kind toward the unthankful and wicked.”
「感謝しない悪人にも
親切」だと言いました
Jesus appreciated this outstanding quality
of his heavenly Father,
イエスは天のお父さんエホバの
親切に感動し
and he imitated God’s kindness.
同じような親切を示しました
What helped Jesus to do so?
どのようにそうしたでしょうか
He treated people in a kind manner
自分がこういうことを言ったら
あるいはこういうことをしたら
by anticipating how his words and actions
相手がどんな気持ちになるだろう と
よく考えたのです
might affect their feelings.
For example, the Bible tells us
ある時 罪人として知られる女性が
that a woman known to be a sinner
approached Jesus,
イエスの所に来て 泣いて
weeping and wetting his feet with her tears.
涙でイエスの足をぬらし始めました
イエスは彼女が悔い改めていることを
見て取りました
Jesus discerned that she was repentant,
and he knew how heartbroken she would be
そして不親切にあしらったら
とても傷つくに違いないと思いました
if he just dismissed her unkindly.
天のお父さんと同じように
Like his heavenly Father,
Jesus looked for the good in her.
この女性の良いところを見たのです
We know this because he commended her;
そして彼女を褒め
then he forgave her.
彼女の罪を許しました
Following Jesus’ example,
私たちもどうすれば
神の親切に倣えるでしょうか
how can we also imitate God’s kindness?
いつでも誰にでも
We can do so by being gentle to all people
whenever possible.
優しく接することによってです
Kind people discern
how to deal with delicate situations.
親切な人は 相手の気持ちを
察することができます
Kind people avoid hurting
the feelings of others.
相手の感情を傷つけないよう
気を付けます
自分がこういうことを言ったら
When we do this, we try to anticipate
こういうことをしたら相手は
どう思うだろうと考えるのです
how our words and actions might affect them.
That is how a true friend of God
will treat others.
神の友達である人は
人にそのように接します
Well, this review of just a few
of Jehovah’s many outstanding qualities
ご一緒にエホバの愛と
親切について考えました
このように聖書を読んで
学んだことを当てはめることは
gives us an idea of how much we can benefit
from reading the Bible
and then applying its many lessons for us.
本当に私たちのためになります
神と友達になることができます
Yes, friendship with God is possible,
and we can imitate his outstanding qualities.
神の素晴らしい性格に
近づくこともできます
次のビデオをご覧ください
In the following video,
please take note of how we can use the Bible
聖書を使ってどのように神との友情を
育てることができるでしょうか
to build a friendship with God.
Have you ever wanted to ask God:
神様にこう祈ったことがありますか
“Who are you?
「もしおられるなら
どこにおられるのですか
“Where are you?
Do you care about me?”
私のことを気に掛けてくれていますか」
You are not alone.
昔から 世界中の多くの人が
For centuries,
人間を造った神について
知りたいと思ってきました
people everywhere have felt the need
to know their Maker.
Imagine a woman
who has never known her father.
父親のことをよく知らない
女性がいたとします
All her life she has been told lies
that her father abandoned her.
「あなたはお父さんに捨てられたのよ」
と言われて育ってきました
But deep inside she feels
—she knows—
でも 心の中では「それは違う」
と感じていました
it’s not true.
ある日 父親から手紙が来ました
One day,
she receives a letter from her father.
手紙を読んで お父さんは生きていて
She learns that he is alive
and that, unbeknownst to her,
自分が生まれた時からずっと気に掛け
he had been reaching out
to be part of her life
助けになりたいと思ってくれていた
ことが分かりました
since the day she was born.
そして お父さんがどこにいるかも
分かりました
The daughter learns who her father is,
and eventually
その後
会うことができました
she finds him.
They learn about one another
お互いのことをよく知って
and build a strong bond
親友のような強い絆が生まれました
until they are inseparable friends.
The Bible is like a group
聖書は お父さんともいえる
神からの手紙のようなものです
of letters from our heavenly Father.
As we read the Bible,
聖書を読むと
we learn how to talk to God,
神にどのように祈れるか
神はどのように答えてくれるか
how he responds,
私たちのことをどれほど気に掛けて
くれているかが分かります
and the many ways
he shows his tender care.
また 考えたこともないような
The Bible can help us to do something
素晴らしいことが可能になる
と言っています
we may never have thought possible
神と友達になれるのです
—be God’s friend.
That friendship starts by learning the name
神と友達になるには
まず名前を知る必要があります
of your heavenly Father and new Friend,
神はその名前を教えてくれています
and God tells us his name:
“You, whose name is Jehovah,
「エホバという名を持つあなただけが
地球全体を治める至高者である」
と言っています
you alone are the Most High.”
そして こう約束してくれています
Jehovah guarantees that if you
「神に近づいてください
‘draw close to him,
そうすれば
神は近づいてくださいます」
he will draw close to you.’
優しいお父さんエホバは
Our loving Father openly extends friendship
神を知ろうとする人を
喜んで友達にしてくれます
to all who search for him.
Will you accept his invitation?
あなたは神の友達になりますか
To learn more about what the Bible says
そのことや ほかの点について
もっと知りたい方は
on this and many other topics,
jw.orgをご覧ください
go to jw.org.
As that thought-provoking video asked,
とても興味深いビデオでした
do you see the need
to come to know your Creator?
あなたも神について
知りたいと思いますか
Are you willing to put forth
the effort needed
あなたも呼び掛けに応じ
to accept his invitation
and become his friend?
神の友達になるために
頑張ってみたいと思いますか
聖書には そのために必要な
アドバイスが書かれています
If so, the Bible contains
the guidance that you need,
and the reward for applying what it says
聖書のアドバイスに従うなら
is not reserved for the future only.
将来 幸せになれます
それだけではありません
Friendship with God brings peace now.
今も幸せになれます
You can have a more peaceful
and meaningful life right now
エホバの友達になるなら今
平和で幸せな生活ができるのです
by becoming Jehovah’s friend.
神の友達になるなら
When you become a friend of God,
he will listen to your prayers
神はあなたの祈りを聞き
憐れみを示してくれます
and extend his mercy to you.
罪が許されていることを知ると
And when you sense his forgiveness,
you will experience deep-seated joy.
深い喜びを味わえます
Psalm 32:1, 2 says in part:
詩編 32:1, 2にはこうあります
“Happy is the one
whose transgression is pardoned,
「違反を許され
罪を覆われる人は幸せだ
“whose sin is covered.
Happy is the man
whom Jehovah does not charge with guilt.”
エホバから罪があると
見なされない人⋯⋯は幸せだ」
What a blessing it is
to sense Jehovah’s forgiveness!
エホバに許してもらえるのは
本当にうれしいことです
God’s forgiveness can free you
from the burden of guilt
以前にしてしまったことのために
罪悪感を抱いているとしても
that you may feel because of past wrongs.
心配は要りません
This includes wrongs
that you may have committed
神を知り 神の友達になる前に
してしまったことは許されます
before you came to know God
and became his friend.
Is such a thing possible for you?
あなたも神に許してもらうことが
できるのです
Yes, it is.
ビデオにあったように 聖書を学ぶと
神にどのように祈れるか
As our video pointed out,
the Bible teaches us how to pray to God
and how God responds to our prayers.
祈りがどのように聞かれるかが
分かります
And you can be assured
that he will listen to your prayers,
また 神の許しや助けを
求める祈りを含め
including your prayers
for his forgiveness and his help.
神が祈りを聞いてくれることを
確信できるでしょう
格言 15:29には
At Proverbs 15:29 we read
エホバは「正しい人の
祈りを聞く」とあります
that Jehovah
“hears the prayer of the righteous.”
Who are the righteous?
正しい人とは
The righteous are those who strive
to live by his requirements.
エホバが求めていることに従って
生きようと努力する人のことです
What a comfort for us to know
that we can be God’s friend,
神の友達になれるのは
本当にうれしいことです
because he sees what we are trying to do
神は私たちの努力に目を留め
祈りを聞いてくださるのです
and he listens to us!
それだけではありません
But there is more.
Our friendship with God can also result
in peace with other people.
神の友達になるなら
他の人との平和な関係も楽しめます
In fact, Jesus urged us
to seek such peace with others.
イエスも他の人と平和な関係で
いるよう勧めました
He said that we should ‘love even our enemies
敵でさえ愛するよう教え
お返しを期待せずに
善を行うようにと言ったのです
and do good to others
without hoping for anything back.’
And then we read at Luke 6:36 that he added:
また ルカ 6:36では
こう言っています
“Continue being merciful,
「天の父が憐れみ深いように
憐れみ深くありなさい」
just as your Father is merciful.”
Such a good example
can touch the hearts of others
そのように努力するなら
人々は心を動かされ
and move them
to become Jehovah’s friends as well.
自分も神の友達になりたいと
思うでしょう
Consider the experience of José,
ホセという男性は
神の友となっている人たちと接し
who learned how to love
from true friends of God.
神と人を愛するようになりました
ホセは13歳の時 ゲリラ活動に
加わるようになりました
At the age of 13, José was involved
in guerrilla warfare.
He was taught to hate the people
who were allegedly responsible
世の中に見られる不公正を嫌い
その原因になっていると思えた人たちを
for the injustices
that he saw all around him.
憎むようになりました
皆殺しにしようと思いました
His aim was to eliminate those people.
He saw many of his companions fall in death,
そして戦いで多くの仲間が命を落とすと
and José became filled
with feelings of bitterness
ますます怒りと復讐心に
燃えるようになりました
and revenge.
手りゅう弾を作りながらこう考えました
While making grenades or bombs,
he would ask himself:
「なぜこんなに苦しみがあるんだろう
‘Why is there so much suffering?
If there is a God, does he even notice?’
神はどうして何もしてくれないんだ？」
ホセは何度も涙を流しました
Many times, José wept.
He was depressed and confused.
混乱し 失望しました
Eventually, José came in contact
ホセはやがて 地元の会衆の
エホバの証人と出会いました
with a local congregation
of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
初めて行った集会で 何て愛にあふれた
雰囲気なんだろうと思いました
At his first congregation meeting,
he noticed the loving atmosphere there.
Everyone greeted him
in a warm and friendly manner.
みんなが温かく歓迎してくれました
Later, a discussion on the subject
しばらくして 神が悪の存在を
許しているのはなぜかについて学び
“Why Does God Permit Wickedness?”
provided answers to the very questions
that he had been asking.
ずっと抱いていた疑問の
答えが分かりました
As he learned more from the Bible,
José made changes
聖書の知識が深まるにつれ
考え方や生き方が変わりました
in his way of life and in his thinking.
神のような愛を身に着けるよう努力し
He learned to imitate God’s love
and thereby become his friend.
神の友達になりました
Breaking his ties with his companions,
though, proved to be challenging.
でも 昔の仲間と関係を断つのは
大変でした
王国会館に行くたびに
Every time he went
to the Kingdom Hall of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
昔の仲間が後をつけてきました
he was followed.
中には集会に出席した人もいます
Some former associates
even attended a few meetings
ホセがどうしてそんなに変わって
しまったのか知りたかったのです
so as to understand what brought about
such a great change in José.
やがて ホセが危険な存在ではない
ことが分かり 干渉しなくなりました
But once they were satisfied
that he was not a danger to them,
they left him alone.
At age 17, José was baptized
as one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
ホセは17歳の時
バプテスマを受けました
As God’s friend,
神の友達になったホセは
José soon started sharing
what he was learning full-time.
全時間 伝道するようになりました
人を殺そうとするのではなく
Instead of scheming to kill people,
愛と希望にあふれたメッセージを
伝えるようになったのです
he could now share a message
of love and of hope with them.
エホバの友達になるなら
What a great reward for choosing
本当に良い結果になります
to become Jehovah’s friend!
Yes, even those who were once enemies
以前は敵だった人たちも
互いに仲良くなり
can learn to be at peace with one another
神の友達になることができます
and be God’s friends.
まとめてみましょう
So, what have we learned?
We have reviewed why friendship with God
まず 神の友達になれるのはなぜか
ということを考えました
is realistic and possible for us.
The Bible tells us that since ancient times,
聖書に書かれている通り
神は昔 何人かの人を友と呼びました
God has called some humans his friends.
We also looked at what God has done
神が私たちとの良い関係を取り戻すため
to heal the breach, or close the gap,
between us and him.
何をしてくれたかも学びました
How has he done so?
神は子であるイエスを
遣わしてくれたのです
By means of his Son.
Through Jesus, Jehovah God provided
the ransom sacrifice
エホバ神はイエスを
贖いの犠牲として与え
that was needed to redeem us from sin.
私たちを罪から解放してくれました
Then, we looked at what you must do
to take advantage
また 神の憐れみを受け
神の友達になるために
of God’s mercy and become his friend.
This includes studying his Word, the Bible,
神の言葉 聖書を学び
神の性格に倣う必要が
あることも学びました
and then imitating his outstanding qualities.
Finally, we considered
そして どうすれば今幸せな生活を送り
how you can find a meaningful life now,
他の人と平和な関係を
持てるかも考えました
as well as true peace with others.
Jehovah promises that his friends
エホバはご自分の友が平和な世界で
永遠に生きられるようにしてくれます
will receive eternal life in peace.
If that is what you yearn for,
あなたもそこで生活したいと
思われませんか
then please accept our invitation
もしそうなら ぜひエホバの証人と
聖書を学ぶようお勧めします
to study the Bible with Jehovah’s Witnesses.
By doing so, you will learn
about an unending future
聖書には 苦しみや悲しみのない世界が
いつまでも続くことが約束されています
when anguish of heart is gone forever,
an unending future
神はご自分の友の顔から涙を拭い去り
in which God will permanently
wipe away tears
いつまでも幸せに暮らせるように
してくれるのです
from the faces of his friends.
That future is not only possible,
これは単なる夢ではありません
神の約束は必ず実現するからです
it is the future that God promises!
Thank you, Brother Cook,
for helping us to see
ありがとうございました
神と友達になるなら
how friendship with God
leads to genuine peace.
平和に暮らせることが分かりました
今 平和を愛する多くの人が
Around the earth, millions are pursuing peace
and building faith in Jehovah God
and his Word, the Bible.
神と聖書に信仰を
持つようになっています
お望みであれば 聖書を
無料で学ぶことができます
If you would like to have Bible discussions,
free of charge,
at a time and place convenient for you,
時間と場所はご都合に合わせられます
please inform one of Jehovah’s Witnesses
エホバの証人にお尋ねになるか
or visit jw.org
jw.orgから聖書レッスンを
お申し込みください
and fill out an online request
for a Bible study.
お近くのエホバの証人が
喜んでお手伝いします
We will be happy to arrange
for one of Jehovah’s Witnesses to assist you.
言語によっては jw.orgに
Additionally, you can find
interactive, self-guided Bible study lessons
自習形式のオンライン聖書講座も
用意されています
on our website, jw.org.
これで 3日目午前の部を終了します
We have reached the conclusion
of this session.
We look forward to the next session
in which we will see
次の部ではドラマを
楽しむことができます
「エホバは平和へと導いてくださる」
というドラマの第2部です
part two of our feature Bible drama,
“Jehovah Guides Us in the Way of Peace{
その後 大会最後の話をお聞きします
and we will hear the final talk
of this convention.
Now let’s sing a song
that expresses our confidence
では 神の約束に対する
確信を強める歌を歌いましょう
in God’s promises.
ご一緒に歌うのは147番の歌です
We invite you to sing
song number 147, entitled
主題は「約束された永遠の命」です
“Life Everlasting Is Promised.”
That’s song number 147,
歌は147番です
その後 それぞれの場所で
祈りを捧げてください
after which you may have
your local concluding prayer.